<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<quack xmlns="http://namespace.operationaldynamics.com/parchment/0.5">
<title>
Todo
</title>
<heading>
File format
</heading>
<text>
The on-disk format needs to be completed, and finalized as
<literal>1.0</literal>.
</text>
<text>
<bold>Launching documents from Nautilus</bold>
</text>
<text>
Once the format is finalized, we need to register a MIME type
with GNOME via a <literal>.desktop</literal> file so that documents
are launched when opened by the <project>Nautilus</project> file
browser or with <command>gnome-open</command> from the command
line.
</text>
<text>
This will probably also require single instance code via [org.gnome.notify]
<type>Notify</type>. We'll need to have a mechanism to differentiate
between development and normal use (start new instance &amp;
terminate existing vs just load into existing instance?).
</text>
<text>
Should individual chapters be launchable, or just the document?
</text>
<heading>
Saving
</heading>
<text>
<bold>Line wrapping of XML output</bold>
</text>
<text>
The line-breaking algorithm in <project>Xom</project> is rather
poor: it takes the maximum line length specified, subtracts 10,
and then looks for a possible line break after that point. This
makes for erratic justification, trailing space characters, and
other artifacts. This is due to <project>Xom</project>'s
<type>Serializer</type> handles its output one character at a
time and has no look ahead / read back capability.
</text>
<text>
It may be better for us to write the output file to a
<type>StringWriter</type> or <type>ByteArrayOutputStream</type>
and then do the breaks manually by doing <literal>' '</literal>
to <literal>'\n' </literal>replacements.
</text>
<text>
For what it's worth, though, it's getting closer to the point
where <italics>not</italics> using <project>Xom</project> and
just doing the really minimal XML work ourselves would be feasible.
Not really that interested going down the not-invented-here road,
but...
</text>
<heading>
User interface
</heading>
<text>
<bold>Editor for notes and references</bold>
</text>
<text>
While loading, display, rendering, and saving of documents with
<literal>&lt;note&gt;</literal> and <literal>&lt;cite&gt;</literal>
tags is implemented, there's no user interface for adding or
creating these markers yet, nor editing the reference bodies.
</text>
<text>
<bold>Document word lists</bold>
</text>
<text>
While we have enabled adding words to the user's custom dictionary
via "Add" in the suggestions menu, it may make sense to add words
to the document. Perhaps this is just "Ignore"?
</text>
<text>
This will likely make more sense when we have a proper notion
of document and can store a word list there.
</text>
<heading>
Copyright
</heading>
<quote>
Copyright © 2008-2010 Operational Dynamics Consulting, Pty Ltd
</quote>
<quote>
As project documentation, this file forms an integral part of
the source code of the program it accompanies, and thus is made
available to you by its authors under the terms of the "GNU General
Public Licence version 2". See the <filename>LICENCE</filename>
file for the terms governing usage, copying and redistribution.
</quote>
</quack>
