<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<quack xmlns="http://namespace.operationaldynamics.com/parchment/5.0">
<division>
The Parchment File Format
</division>
<text/>
<text/>
<leader>
Abstract
</leader>
<quote>
<italics>The on-disk file format used by the</italics>
<project>Quill</project><italics> what-you-see-is-what-you-need
document editor and presented by the</italics>
<project>Parchment</project><italics> what-you-get-is-what-you-want
rendering engine is a little unconventional: it's text based, so you
can use version control. The schema is extraordinarily simplistic,
meaning that it can be worked with programmatically. More importantly,
it can be fixed by humans when it breaks. And finally, the format is
actually designed to support technical writing and technical
writers.</italics>
</quote>
<quote>
<italics>Not to worry; this is not the dawn of the millennium; the
program will probably crash and eat your data. All is as it should
be.</italics>
</quote>
<quote>
<italics>But if you're interested in the design decisions that led to
the Parchment File Format being what it is, then you will find here
some background along with our documentation of the "Manuscript
Schema" (found in the </italics>
<literal>.parchment</literal><italics> files), and the "Quack Schema"
(the chapters in </italics><literal>.xml</literal><italics> files that
make up those manuscripts).</italics>
</quote>
<quote/>
<text/>
<text/>
<text/>
<text>
Copyright © 2010 Operational Dynamics Consulting, Pty Ltd.
</text>
<text>
This document describes the file format used for storing chapters
created by the <project>Quill and Parchment</project> suite of
programs along with the metadata files used to describe documents as a
whole.
</text>
<text>
As such, this file forms an integral part of the source code of the
program it accompanies, and is made available to you by its authors
under the terms of the <title>GNU General Public Licence version
2</title>. See the <filename>LICENCE</filename> file for the terms
governing usage, copying and redistribution.
</text>
<text>
Although you have the freedom to use the information in this document
in accordance with this licence, the schema it describes is controlled
by the <acronym>XML</acronym> Standards Team at Operational Dynamics.
Changes will only be made after public consultation and in correlation
with support in the <project>Quill and Parchment</project> application
for such new schema versions to ensure forward and backwards
compatibility.
</text>
</quack>
